Guide to the James S. Allen Papers TAM.142
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
James S. Allen Papers
1920-1994
1945-1970
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Allen, James S.
Auerbach, Jesse
TAM.142
8 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, and 2 folders in a flat-file drawer.
James S. Allen, born Sol Auerbach (1906-1986), was an organizer, Marxist scholar, writer and editor for the Communist Party, USA. He was a doctoral candidate in philosophy at the University of Pennsylvania and was in the first American student delegation to the Soviet Union. In 1928, he joined the Communist Party and began writing for the Daily Worker. He was a leading party organizer in the south in the early 1930s, and edited the Labor Defender and Southern Worker. In the late 1930's, he travelled to the Phillippines where he helped to arrange the merger of the socialist and Communist parties. His books include: The Negro Question in the United States (1936), Atomic Energy and Society (1949), and Organizing in the Depression South: A Communist's Memoir (2001). From 1962 to 1972, Allen also headed International Publishers, the CPUSA publishing house. The collection includes his correspondence, Communist Party documents, photographs, and scrapbooks.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by James S. Allen in 1982; addional materials were donated by Jesse Auerbach in 1986 and 2013. The accession numbers associated with this gift is 1982.009 and 2014.011.
Appraisal
Duplicates of Allen's biography for his memorial were removed from the 2014 accession.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series:
Series I: Biographical and Correspondence
Series II: Communist Party, USA New Program Committee
Series III: FOIA Files
Series IV: Philippines
Series V: Subject Files
Series VI: Writings
Series VII: Scrapbooks and Charts
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically within each series. A portion of the correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Historical/Biographical Note
James S. Allen (1906-1986), an organizer, Marxist scholar, writer and editor for the Communist Party, USA, was born Sol Auerbach in Philadelphia in 1906, the year his parents, Jacob and Luba, who were Russian Jewish radicals, came to the U.S. A doctoral candidate in philosophy at the University of Pennsylvania, he traveled in 1927 with the first American student delegation to the Soviet Union. In 1928 he was expelled from college for his radical activities, joined the Communist Party and began writing for the Daily Worker, and edited the Labor Defender. In 1930, he took the pen name by which he became known and, with his wife Isabelle, founded and edited the Southern Worker, the first Communist weekly published in the South, which was circulated on an underground basis. As a member of the Party's Southern District committee, Allen played a prominent role in all of the CPUSA's major regional activities during the early 1930s; the organizing of Alabama sharecroppers, the Harlan, Kentucky miners' strike and the Scottsboro case.
Three books by Allen, The Negro Question in the United States (1936), Reconstruction: The Battle for Democracy (1937), and American Communism and Black Americans (with Philip Foner, 1987), reflect his political concerns and southern experiences. By 1931, the strain of underground political work caused Allen to leave the South. In the late 1930s he was CPUSA representative in the Philippines, and a correspondent for The Nation (per a letter by editor Max Lerner), where he helped obtain the release of Communist prisoners and helped achieve the merger of the Communist and Socialist Parties. He served as foreign editor of the Daily Worker until being drafted in 1944.
During the Cold War years, he served as foreign editor of the Sunday Worker and was compelled to appear as a witness before the House Un-American Activities Committee. During the years 1958-1966, Allen was the secretary of the Party's National Program Committee, which was charged with developing a new program for the CPUSA, and he authored the initial drafts of the program, which was not published until 1970, and corresponded with prominent communists including Herbert Aptheker, William Z. Foster, John Howard Lawson, Pettis Perry and Al Richmond. From 1962 to 1972 Allen headed International Publishers, the CPUSA publishing house, having assisted his predecessor Alexander Trachtenberg, over the previous decades. He later served as U.S. editor of the Collected Works of Marx and Engels, a joint undertaking with English and Soviet publishers, corresponding with the British Marxist philosopher Maurice Cornforth. Allen also wrote several polemical books and pamphlets, including Atomic Energy and Society (1949), which elicited a signed letter from Albert Einstein, and several unpublished manuscripts, including a memoir titled "Visions and Revisions," a portion of which was posthumously published as Organizing in the Depression South: A Communist's Memoir (2001).
James Allen Bibliography: Books & Pamphlets
American Communism and Black Americans: A Documentary History, 1919-1929, edited by Philip S. Foner and James S. Allen (Philadelphia: Temple University Press, 1987), 235 p.
The American Negro (New York: International Pamphlets, 1932), 31p.
Atomic Energy and Society (New York, International Publishers, 1949), 95 p.
Atomic Imperialism: The State, Monopoly, and the Bomb (New York, International Publishers, 1952), 288 p.
The Cartel System, (New York: International Publishers, c1946), 32 p.
Conference on Managed Economy, The Cold War and the Developing Economic Crisis, 1949: Jefferson School of Social Science, New York, The economic crisis and the cold war; reports, edited by James S. Allen and Doxey A. Wilkerson, with an introductory essay by William Z. Foster (New York, New Century Publishers, 1949), 113 p.
The Crisis in India, (New York: Workers Library Publishers, 1942), 31 p.
Disarmament and the American Economy: A Symposium, James S. Allen, et al, edited by Herbert Aptheker (New York: New Century Publishers, 1960), 64 p.
The Economic Crisis and the Cold War, edited by James S. Allen and Doxey A. Wilkerson: with an introductory essay by William Z. Foster (New York: New Century Publishers, 1949), 113 p.
The Lessons of Cuba, (New York: New Century Publishers, 1961), 31 p.
Marshall Plan: Recovery or War, (New York: New Century Publishers, 1948), 64 p.
Negro Liberation, (New York: International Publishers, 1938), 46 p.
The Negro Question in the United States (New York, International Publishers, 1936), 224 p..
The Negroes in a Soviet America (New York: Workers Library Publishers, 1935), 46 p. By James W. Ford and James S. Allen.
On Democratic Centralism: Name and Form, (S.l.: s.n., 19-), 6 p.
Organizing in the Depression South: A Communist's Memoir, (Minneapolis, Minn.: MEP Publications, 2001), 145 p.
The Philippine Left on the Eve of World War II, foreword by William Pomeroy, 2nd ed., (Minneapolis: MEP Publications, 1993), 167 p.
The Radical Left on the Eve of War: A Political Memoir Quezon City, Philippines: Foundation for Nationalist Studies, 1985), 121 p.
Reconstruction: The Battle for Democracy (1865-1876) (New York, International Publishers, 1937), 256 p.
Smash the Scottsboro Lynch Verdict (New York: Workers Library Publishers, 1933), 16 p.
Thomas Paine: Selections from his Writings, with an introduction, by James S. Allen (New York: International Publishers, 1937), 96 p.
The United States and the Common Market (New York: New Century Publishers, 1962), 36 p.
Who Owns America? (New York, New Century Publishers, 1946), pamphlet.
World Cooperation for Post-War Prosperity (New York, New Century publishers, 1945), 63 p.
World Monopoly and Peace (New York, International Publishers 1946), 288 p.
James Allen Bibliography: Articles
"America and neutrality," National issues: A survey of politics and legislation, 1 (1939), 13-16.
"American imperialism and the war," Communism, 18 (1939), 1046-1053.
"The American road to Socialism," Political Affairs, 37 (1958), 8-27.
"Awakening in the cotton belt," New Masses, 8 (1932), 11-12.
"The black belt: area of Negro majority," Communist, 13 (1934), 581-599.
"Bretton Woods and world security," Communist, 23 (1944), 1078-1086.
"The Communist way out," Crisis, 42 (1935), 134-135.
"Democratic revival and the Marxists," Masses & Mainstream, 8 (1955), 1-11.
"Enlightened American imperialism in the Philippines," Political Affairs, 25 (1946), 526-540.
"The far eastern front in the war against the axis," Communist, 21 (1942), 143-162.
"Farm production for defense," Communist, 20 (1941), 910-916.
"The farmers and the struggle against the war program," Communist, 19 (1940), 628-648.
"Lenin and the American Negro," Communist, 13 (1934), 53-61.
"The Negro question," Political Affairs, 25 (1946), 1132-1150.
"The new state in the Far East," Political Affairs, 24 (1945), 441-447.
"The new war economy," Political Affairs, 27 (1948), 1055-1074.
"The Pacific front in the global war," Communist, 21 (1942), 1012-1020.
"The policy of anti-Soviet encirclement," Political Affairs, 26 (1947), 563-570.
"Problems of foreign policy," Political Affairs, 36 (1957), 19-31.
"Prologue to the liberation of the Negro," Communist, 12 (1933), 147-170.
"The Scottsboro struggle," Communist, 12 (1933), 437-448.
"Some lessons of the fateful decade," Communist, 22 (1943), 258-265.
"The Soviet nations and Teheran," Communist, 23 (1944), 206-216.
"We can win in 1943," Communist, 22 (1943), 680-687.
"The world assembly at San Francisco," Political Affairs, 24 (1945), 291-301.
Allen wrote the initial draft for the following works, and played a leading role in the Communist Party's Program Committee, which was responsible for drafting them --
Communist Party of the United States of America, New program of the Communist Party, U. S.A.; a draft (New York, Political Affairs Publishers, 1966), 127 p.
Communist Party of the United States of America, New program of the Communist Party U.S.A. (New York, New Outlook Publishers, 1970), 128 p.
Scope and Content Note
The collection documents James Allen's life-long involvement in the Communist Party, particularly his leadership of the National Program Committee and his work in the Philippines, in the form of correspondence, notes, research materials, photographs, minutes, drafts, and other materials. Manuscripts and typescripts document Allen's writing career, especially in regards to his autobiography and his works on politics and race relations in the South. The collection also includes biographical information on Allen and materials related to his early and personal life. A small amount of material was created or collected by Allen's wife, Isabelle Auerbach, and reflects her involvement with the Communist Party and other political causes.
Notes.; Documents.; Correspondence.; Communists -- United States.; International relations.; Economics.; Photographs.; African Americans.; Clippings (information artifacts); Strikes and lockouts |z United States.; Communism |z Cuba |x History |v Sources.; Communism |z Philippines |x History |v Sources.; Communism -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Charts (graphic documents).; Printed ephemera.; Scrapbooks.; Hall, Gus; Aptheker, Herbert, 1915-2003.; Allen, James S.; Perry, Pettis. -- |v Portraits; Lumer, Hyman; Auerbach, Isabelle; Auerbach, Jacob; Auerbach, Luba; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961.; Gates, John, 1913-; Cornforth, Maurice Campbell; Lawson, John Howard, 1894-1977.; Communist Party of the United States of America. Agrarian Commission; Marx, Karl, 1818-1883; Haga, Takeshi; Jackson, James; Communist Party of the United States of America -- History; Communist Party of the United States of America. National Program Committee; Communist Party of the United States of America. Negro Commission; International Publishers; Roca Calderio, Blas; Wilkerson, Doxey Alphonso, 1905-1993.; Pomeroy, William J., 1916-; Richmond, Al, 1913-1987.; Communist Party of the United States of America; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955.; Auerbach, Jesse
- Series I: Correspondence and Biographical and Family Papers, 13479
  Scope and Content Note
  The Biographical and Correspondence series is divided into two subseries, alphabetical and chronological, and principally consists of correspondence. Notable are a file of 1938 correspondence between Allen and his wife, Isabelle Auerbach, much of it written during his trip to the Philippines; correspondence with William Z. Foster, who sought Allen's advice regarding his writings; a polemical exchange with Hyman Lumer, regarding his War Economy and Crisis (1954); correspondence with Japanese Marxist publisher Takeshi "Fred" Haga; some of Allen's student writings; and a file on his dismissal in 1928 from his position as a philosophy instructor at the University of Pennsylvania. Also included is some of Isabelle Auerbach's later correspondence, mostly pertaining to her work with International Publishers.
  - Subseries A: Alphabetical, 13493
    - Auerbach, Isabelle: Correspondence, 1938; 13511 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Auerbach, Isabelle: Correspondence, 1968-1972; 544695; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - Auerbach, Isabelle, Death of: Correspondence, 1971-1973; 13510 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Auerbach, Sol and Isabelle (re: Communist Party Issues and the Great Depression): Correspondence, 1928-1931; 544696; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - Allen, James, 60th Birthday Celebration: Correspondence, 1966; 13509 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Auerbach, Jesse (son): Correspondence, 1962; 13508 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Biography for Memorial, circa 1986; 544697; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - College Compositions, 1923-1927; 13507 (Box 1, Folder 4A)
    - Daily Worker (lengthy "Anti-Gates" letter to the editor), ca.1956-1958; 13506 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - FOIA: Correspondence, 1977-1985; 13505 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Foster, William Z.: Correspondence (re: Outline Political History of the Americas), 1950; 13504 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Haga, Takeshi ("Fred"): Correspondence, 1969-1974; 13503 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lumer, Hyman (re: War Economy and Crisis): Correspondence, 1953; 13502 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Marx and Engels Collected Works: Correspondence, Alphabetical, 1969-1976; 13501 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Marx and Engels Collected Works: Correspondence - Cornforth, Maurice, 1969-1976; 13500 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Mins, Henry (translator, Marx and Engels Collected Works): Correspondence, 1973-1975; 13499 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Passport: Correspondence, 1959-1966; 13498 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Pennsylvania, University of: Allen's Loss of Instructorship, 1928; 13497 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Poems and Jottings, 1920-1927; 13496 (Box 1, Folder 14A)
    - U.S. Senate Committee on Government Operations: Allen testimony, 1953-1957; 13495 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - What's in a Name? (Re: Allen/Auerbach), undated; 13494 (Box 1, Folder 15A)
  - Subseries B: Chronological, 13480
    - Correspondence, 1935-1948; 13492 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1951-1959; 13491 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1969; 13490 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1971; 13489 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1972; 13488 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1973; 13487 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1975; 13486 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1976-1977; 13485 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1979; 13484 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1981; 13483 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1983; 13482 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1986; 13481 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Series II. Communist Party USA New Program, 13452
  The Program Committee series contains, in addition to numerous drafts authored and/or edited by Allen, correspondence with prominent communists, minutes and other Committee documents, notes taken at CP National Executive Committee Meetings (1960), a brief unpublished typescript by William Z. Foster "Notes on the Communist Party Electoral Policy" (1958) with annotations by Allen, and programmatic materials of other communist parties.
  - Allen: The American Road to Socialism - Program Questions and Political Affairs Article, 1958; 13478 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Allen: Communist Party National Executive Committee Meeting Notes, 1960; 13477 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Allen: Correspondence (Alphabetical), 1958-1959, 1965; 13476 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Allen: Correspondence (re: American Road to Socialism), ca.1958; 13475 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Allen: Correspondence (First Name Only), 1958-1959; 13474 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Allen: How to Move Forward for NC Meeting; March 1960., 13473 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Allen: Initial Report on Basic Program (for the Initiating Committee on Program to the NEC); May 9, 1938, 13472 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Allen: Programmatic Typescripts and Notes, Misc., 1954, 1960-1969; 13471 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Allen: Recovery from the Struggle Against Revisionism (Drafts and Reply to Foster), 1960; 13470 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Allen: Ultra-Right Danger - Notes, 1961-1962; 13469 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - The American Road to Socialism: Program Questions (For Publication in September 1958 Issue of Political Affairs), undated; 13468 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - The American Way to Jobs, Democracy: Draft Program of the Communist Party; Mar-1954, 13467 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - The American Way to Jobs, Peace, Equal Rights, and Democracy: Program of the Communist Party; Sep-1954, 13466 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Communist Party Program Committee Records, 1958-1959; 13465 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Comments from Party Members, undated; 13464 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Communist Party Program Committee - Anti-Monopoly Subcommittee, 1958; 13463 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Communist Party Working Commission Draft Program, Gus Hall cover letter c. Oct 1965, ca.1965; 13462 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Draft: "Declaration of Principles" and "Guiding Elements", undated; 13461 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Foreign Communist Party Programs, 1957-1958; 13460 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Foster, William Z: "Notes on the Communist Party Electoral Policy" (unpublished), Allen's Editorial Notes Thereon; Nov-1958, 13459 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Marxism and the World Today Discussion Guide (Issued by Lecture and Information Bureau), undated; 13458 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - N ew Program of the Communist Party U.S.A.: Adopted by the 19th National Convention (1969), 1970; 13457 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - New Program of the Communist Party U.S.A. (Untitled 'First' Draft), ca.1965-1966; 13456 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - New Program of the Communist Party U.S.A. (Second Draft); Mar-1968, 13455 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Southern People's Program for Democracy, Prosperity, and Peace (CPUSA Southern Regional Committee); Mar-1953, 13454 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Soviet Union Communist Party 22nd Congress - Published Documents and Commentary, 1961; 13453 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Series III: FOIA Files, 13442
  The FOIA series contains some 1500 pages of FBI files (received in the 1980s) which document Allen's activities in the 1950s.
  - Auerbach, FOIA Correspondence and Reports, 1984-1985; 13451 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Auerbach, FOIA File # 100-3-104-34 Sections 7 and 8, undated; 13450 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Auerbach, FOIA File # 100-28831 Section #7, undated; 13449 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Auerbach, FOIA File # 100-28831 Section #8, undated; 13448 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Auerbach, FOIA File # 100-28831 Section #9, undated; 13447 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Auerbach, FOIA File # 100-28831 Section #10, undated; 13446 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Auerbach, FOIA File # 100-28831 Section #11, undated; 13445 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Auerbach, FOIA File # 100-28831 Section #12, undated; 13444 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Auerbach, FOIA Supplemental release of Documents, undated; 13443 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Philippines, 13433
  The Philippines series contains Allen's lengthy 1939 report on his work there; accompanying notes and documents; his correspondence regarding arrangements for his trip and subsequent correspondence, much of it regarding the writing and publication of Allen's The Radical Left on the Eve of War (1985); some correspondence with William J. Pomeroy, a Communist and author of several books about the Philippines; photographs from Allen's time in the Philippines, intended for use in his memoir; an untitled thesis by Antonio S. Araneta, Jr. (c1965) on the history of Communism in the Philippines; and an untitled anonymous book-length typescript on the same subject (possibly by Allen). A file of correspondence, working drafts, articles, and other materials created or collected by Isabelle Auerbach on the subject of the Philippines is also included.
  - Araneta, Antonio S., Jr. Untitled Thesis on Communism in the Philippines, 163 pp., undated; 13441 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Auerbach, Isabelle re: Philippines, 1951-1972; 544701; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Communism in the Commonwealth: A Political Memoir (Allen), 1983; 13440 (Box 3, Folder 4A)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1940, 1958; 13439 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re The Radical Left on the Eve of War (Renato Constantino, William Henry Scott), 1983-1985; 13438 (Box 3, Folder 5A)
  - Correspondence - Pomeroy, William, 1979; 13437 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Philippines, Report on (by Allen) - 45 pp + documents; 13-Feb 1939, 13436 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Philippines: Notes and Documents, undated; 13435 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Philippines: Photographs, circa 1930-1939; 544702; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Untitled, Anonymous Book-Length Typescript on Communism in the Philippines, undated; 13434 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series V: Subject Files, 13381
  The Subject files contain notes, journals and other materials from Allen's trips to the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe (1960-61), and various documents, ephemera, research materials and notes, mostly on post-WWII economic and political topics, although there is some material from Allen's time in the South. The file on the Cuban Revolution contains a lengthy report by Allen dated November, 1957. A notable file, Agrarian Commission (CPUSA), contains letters (including several from sharecroppers), minutes (attendees included Puro, Haywood, Ware), position statements, reports, and other internal documents describing local farm organizing conditions in the South and the Midwest in the early 1930s.
  - Agrarian Commission, CPUSA (see also: box 3, folder 29A), 1931-1933; 13432 (Box 3, Folder 9A)
  - Anti-Monopoly Program, 1956-1959; 13431 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Automation, 1958-1960; 13430 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - China, 1960; 13429 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - China: An Analytical Study of the Financial Basis of the Chinese Kuomintang Clique, ca.1948; 13428 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - China, Communism in, 1946-1950; 13427 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Class Composition, 1959-1960; 13426 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Communist Party USA: Convention, 20th - Draft Theses, Reports, etc., 1971-1972; 13425 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Communist Party USA: Convention, 21st - Draft Main Political Resolution, Feb. 1, 1975., 13424 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Communist Party USA: Crisis, 1954-1958; 13423 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Communist Party USA: Documents, 1960; 13422 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Communist Party USA: Economic Conference, ca.1949; 13421 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Communist Party USA: Education Department (Includes Discussion of Mainstream), 1960-1961; 13420 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Cuba, 1961; 13419 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Cuban Revolution, 1957-1961; 13418 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Eastern Europe: Nationalization - Post WW II, 1945-1948; 13417 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Economic Crisis: Post WWII, ca.1947; 13416 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Elections of 1956: Economic Program, etc., 1955-1956; 13415 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Euro-Communism, ca.1975-1976; 13414 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Europe, Trip, 1964; 13413 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Farm Crisis, 1960; 13412 (Box 3, Folder 29)